I’d like to dedicate this one to all the women in South Africa --
Quisiera dedicar esta canción a todas las mujeres sudafricanas;
those women who refused to dwindle in the midst of apartheid.
a esas mujeres que no cedieron durante el apartheid.
And, of course, I’m dedicating it also to my grandmother,
Y, por supuesto, se la dedico también a mi abuela
whom I think really played quite a lot of important roles,
que pienso realmente tuvo un papel muy importante
especially for me when I was an activist, and being harassed by the police.
sobre todo en mi época de activista cuando era perseguido por la policía.
You will recall that in 1976, June 16, the students of South Africa boycotted
Ustedes recordarán que el 16 de junio de 1976 los estudiantes sudafricanos boicotearon
the language of Afrikaans as the medium of the oppressor, as they were sort of like really told
el idioma africaans por considerarlo un instrumento del opresor; ya saben, tenían instrucciones
that they must do everything in Afrikaans --
de hacer todo en africaans --
biology, mathematics -- and what about our languages? And the students wanted to speak to the government,
biología, matemáticas. ¿Y nuestros idiomas? Los estudiantes querían hablar con el gobierno
and police answered with bullets.
pero la policía les respondió con balas.
So every year, June 16, we will commemorate
Por eso cada 16 de junio conmemoramos
all those comrades or students who died.
a todos aquellos camaradas o estudiantes que murieron.
And I was very young then. I think I was 11 years,
Yo era muy pequeño, pienso que tenía 11 años,
and I started asking questions, and that’s when my political education started.
y comencé a hacer preguntas. Y así comenzó mi educación política
And I joined, later on, the youth organization
Más tarde ingresé a la organización juvenil que
under the African National Congress.
era parte del Congreso Nacional Africano.
So as part of organizing this and whatever,
Entonces, mientras organizábamos algo,
this commemoration, the police will round us up
una conmemoración, la policía nos cercaba,
as they call us leaders.
ya saben, por considerarnos líderes.
And I used to run away from home, when I know that maybe the police might be coming
Y yo solía huir de casa cuando calculaba que ya vendría la policía,
around the ninth or 10th of June or so.
cerca del 9 ó 10 de junio o así.
And my grandmother one time said,
Pero mi abuela, saben, una vez dijo:
"No, look, you’re not going to run away.
"No, mira, no vas a huir".
This is your place, you stay here."
"Este es tu lugar y aquí te quedas".
And indeed, the police came -- because they’ll just arrest us
Y, de hecho, vino la policía – porque nos arrestarían,
and put us in jail and release us whenever they feel like, after the 20th or so.
nos encarcelarían, para liberarnos cuando quisieran, después del 20 más o menos.
So it was on the 10th of June, and they came, and they surrounded the house,
Fue así que el 10 de junio vinieron y rodearon la casa.
and my grandmother switched off all the lights in the house,
Mi abuela apagó todas las luces
and opened the kitchen door.
y abrió la puerta de la cocina.
And she said to them, "Vusi's here, and you're not going to take him tonight.
Y les dijo: "Vusi está aquí pero esta noche no se lo van a llevar".
I'm tired of you having to come here, harassing us,
"Estoy cansada de que vengan aquí a acosarnos...
while your children are sleeping peacefully in your homes.
mientras sus hijos duermen tranquilos en sus casas".
He is here, and you're not going to take him.
"Él está aquí y ustedes no se lo van a llevar".
I've got a bowl full of boiling water -- the first one who comes in here, gets it."
“Tengo agua hirviendo lista para el primero que se acerque".
And they left.
Y se fueron.
(Applause) (Music)
(Aplausos)